Guide to the James Payne Alter Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
James Payne Alter Papers
1817-1984
RG 84
Yale University Divinity School Library
15
(34 boxes)
The papers document Alter's lifelong involvement with the Christian church in India, his affiliation with Yale University, his activities in student Christian organizations, and his ongoing interest in issues of peace and social concern. James Payne Alter was born in India in 1919, son of Presbyterian missionaries. He attended Yale University and Yale Divinity School. He was appointed as a Presbyterian missionary to India in 1945. He taught at Ewing Christian College in Allahabad, served as first Director of the ecumenical Christian Retreat and Study Center, Rajpur, and wrote on Christianity in northern India.
Alter, James P., 1919-
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Barbara Beach Alter.
Biographical / Historical
1919 Oct 14 Born in Sialkot, Punjab, India to David Emmett Alter and Martha Payne Alter; his parents were missionaries of the former United Presbyterian Church of North America.
1929-1933 Attended Woodstock School, Mussourie, India
1933-1936 Attended Mount Hermon School, Massachusetts
1936-1940 Attended Yale University, B.A. 1940
1940-1942 Secretary of Yale University Christian Association
1940-1941 Three month prison term at Danbury Correctional Center as Conscientious Objector
1941-1942 Attended Yale Divinity School
1942 Married Barbara Beach, daughter of David Nelson Beach II. (Children: Martha (1944), John (1947), and Thomas (1950))
1942-1944 Student Pastor, Haydenburg, Tennessee, Cumberland Mountain Presbytery under the auspices of the Presbyterian Board of National Missions
1944-1945 Continued studies at Yale Divinity School
1945 Assigned to the mission field in India by the Board of Foreign Missions of the Presbyterian Church in U.S.A. Arrived in India October, 1945
1946-1947 Attended Leonard Theological College, Jabalpur, India
1947-1951 Professor of English, Chaplain, and Chair of the Department of religion and ethics, Ewing Christian College, Allahabad, India
1949 Ordained by the Allahabad Church Council of the United Church of North India
1951-1952 Continued studies at Yale Divinity School, B.D. 1952
1952-1953 Served as Study Secretary for the World Council of Churches
1954-1968 First Director of ecumenical Christian Retreat and Study Centre, Rajpur, India
1968-1983 Researched, traveled, and published articles relating to the history of North Indian Christianity
1980 Left India on medical retirement
1983 Nov 7 Died
1986 In the Doab and Rohilkhand: north Indian Christianity 1815-1915 (Delhi: ISPCK, 1986.) published posthumously, revised and completed by John Alter, son of JPA
Scope and Contents
James Alter's lifelong involvement with the Christian church in India, his affiliation with Yale University, his activities in student Christian organizations, and his ongoing interest in issues of peace and social concern combine to make this record group a valuable addition to collections held at the Yale Divinity School Library.
Alter's student years at Yale, his involvement in the interrelated student Christian groups of that era, and his experiences as a conscientious objector during the Second World War are well documented. After his return to India, extensive correspondence, writings and collected material provide important information about people and events as well as providing insight into Alter's personal journey as a son of traditional Presbyterian missionaries returning to devote his own life to an evolving participation in and understanding of the Christian church in north India. This record group does not contain a great deal of material relating specifically to the Christian Retreat and Study Centre in Rajpur, which Alter directed from 1954 to 1968. His consulting activities and research after this period are well documented.
The Correspondence of Series I, dating from 1936 to 1983, is divided into Family Correspondence and General Correspondence. Correspondence with family members, particularly his parents, is frequent and substantive. These letters, combined with the circular letters prepared by Jim and Barry Alter for their family and friends, provide thorough documentation of their activities for four decades. A fair portion of the General Correspondence is with the Presbyterian mission board and Presbyterian churches throughout the U.S. that provided financial support for the Alters. Also included in the General Correspondence section are letters documenting Alter's involvement in student Christian work, peace groups, and ecumenical ventures.
Series II is comprised of writings by Alter, including unpublished manuscripts, student papers, book reviews, sermons, lectures, and published works. The majority of the unpublished manuscripts and drafts contained in this Series relate to Christianity in northern India. Many are also available in published form, but drafts have been retained to document changes and revisions.
The materials contained in Series III and Series IV are similar in many ways, but Series III, Research Materials, represents the files that Alter had intentionally gathered together to support his ongoing research. These research materials relate almost exclusively to Christianity in northern India or to the interaction between Christianity and Communism. They include articles, reports, letters, notes, and newspaper clippings.
The Collected Material of Series IV is similar in format but covers a broader range of subject matter. Some materials relate to Christianity in India while others relate to courses taken by Alter, peace groups such as the Fellowship of Reconciliation, student Christian groups, and other organizations with which Alter was affiliated throughout his life, including the United Presbyterian Church Commission on Ecumenical Mission and Relations and the World Council of Churches.
Series V, Biographical Material, is an attempt to gather together and organize a hodge-podge of documentation relating to trips, projects, and other events in Alter's life. The Series includes notes, reports, itineraries, photographs, and official documents.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Research Materials
IV. Collected Material
V. Biographical Material
Missions -- India; Missionaries; Alter, James P., 1919-; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A -- Missions -- India
- Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Letters are grouped in two sections, family and general correspondence and are arranged alphabetically by sender or recipient other than Alter. Frequent or notable correspondents are listed separately while less substantial correspondence is grouped under the first letter of the
  sender or recipient's surname.
  - Family correspondence
    - Alter, Barbara "Barry" [wife], 1942-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
    - Alter, Barbara "Barry" [wife], 1964-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13-16)
    - Alter, David Emmett and Martha Payne [parents], 1939-1954 (Box 2, Folder 17-24)
    - Alter, David E. and Cleo [brother], 1940-1979 (Box 3, Folder 25-27)
    - Alter, Dean and Dondee [brother], 1966-1979 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Alter, Dismore and Ada [uncle], 1940-1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Alter, Jeanette C. [grandmother], 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Alter, Joe [brother], 1940-1952 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
    - Alter, Joe and Marian, 1953-1979 (Box 3, Folder 33-35)
    - Alter, Joe [to/from friend Corinne Scott], 1942 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Alter, Joseph [uncle], 1940-1967 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Alter, John [son], 1962-1972 (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
    - Alter, John and Sandi, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Alter, John and Sandi, 1976-1980 (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
    - Alter, Margaret [aunt], 1940-1951 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Alter, Margaret B. [aunt], 1967-1978 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Alter, Martha "Marty" [daughter];see also under Chen, 1960-1967 (Box 4, Folder 45-47)
    - Alter, Martha Payne [mother];see also under David Emmett and Martha Payne Alter, 1954-1968 (Box 4, Folder 48-53)
    - Alter, Martha Payne [mother], 1969-1978 (Box 5, Folder 54-59)
    - Alter, Robert and Ellen [brother], 1942-1979 (Box 5, Folder 60-62)
    - Alter, Thomas [son], 1962-1974 (Box 5, Folder 63-65)
    - Alter, Thomas [son], 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 66-67)
    - Alter, Ward and Mary [cousins], 1962-1979 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Beach, Alice Cary [aunt?], 1942 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Beach, Mr. Mrs. David Nelson Jr. [parents of BBA], 1941-1979 (Box 6, Folder 70-71)
    - Beach, Mr. David Nelson III and Jan [brother of BBA], 1963-1975 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Beach, Dorthea [aunt], 1942 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Chen, Martha "Marty" [daughter] and Lincoln; see also above, "Marty" Alter, 1967-1979 (Box 6, Folder 74-76)
    - Chen, Samuel [father of Lincoln Chen], 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - McAllister, Alex and Janet [cousins] see also Janet Wien, 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Payne, Evangeline Wien [aunt], 1940-1952 (Box 6, Folder 79-80)
    - Payne, Grandma [grandmother], 1940-1948 (Box 6, Folder 81-82)
    - Strickland, Ida Alter [cousin], 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Wien, Janet [cousin], 1950, 1962-1975 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Family correspondence to JPA while in prison at Danbury Federal Correctional Institution, Danbury Connecticut [includes limited correspondence with fellow inmates], 1940 Dec 8-1941 Mar (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - "Family" [circular letters from JPA], 1959-1980 (Box 6, Folder 86-87)
    - Miscellaneous family correspondence (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - General correspondence
    - A (Box 7, Folder 89)
    - Abrams, Robert W., 1963, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    - Alpine Young Peoples Society, TN, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - American Friends Service Committee, 1940-1943 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Amritanand, Right Rev. J., Bishop of Lucknow, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - Association for Asian Studies, 1969-1976 (Box 7, Folder 94)
    - B (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - Bainton, Roland H., 1971, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Baksh, Victor, 1978-1979 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - Baksh, Victor, 1980-1983 (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - Barbour, Hugh S., 1941-1942, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 99)
    - Barker, William P., 1964 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    - Barnabas, A. L., 1977-1979 (Box 7, Folder 101)
    - Barstow, Robbins W. and Mrs., 1941, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 102)
    - Bathgate, John, 1948-1978 (Box 7, Folder 103)
    - Beach, Mr. and Mrs. Harry R., 1977-1979 (Box 7, Folder 104)
    - Bethany Presbyterian Church, Huntington Station, NY, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Bhandare, Bishop R. S., 1969-1982 (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Bhatty, E. C., 1962-1970 (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - Bible Society of India, 1959-1974 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Bilheimer, Robert Sperry, 1938-1976 (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Blackshear, Rev. David S., 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Broadway United Church of Christ, NY, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Bundy, McGeorge, 1940-1982 (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - C (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - Campbell, E. Fay, 1942, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 114)
    - Campbell, Ernest Y., 1960-1980 (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Chand, Bhag, 1978-1983 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Christian Missionary in North India, 1948-1949 (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - Christian Retreat and Study Centre, 1962-1983 (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - Christian Rural Fellowship, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - Christianity and Crisis, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Church History Association of India, 1968-1974 (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Church History Association of India, 1975-1982 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Church of Scotland Missions, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Church, Frank, Senator, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Cole, John R., 1969, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Committee on Social Action, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - Converse, Hyla S., 1974-1979 (Box 8, Folder 127)
    - Cory, Robert H., 1942 (Box 8, Folder 128)
    - D (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - Daniel, Samson A., 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - David, Rev. Dr. C. W., 1958-1959, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 131)
    - Dayal, Right Rev. Din, 1954-1982 (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - Dellinger, David, 1940, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Dilworth, Rev. Dr. David E., 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 134)
    - Dodds, Robert C. and Elisabeth D., 1940-1978 (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - Downs, Frederick S., 1974-1983 (Box 8, Folder 136)
    - Durgin, Larry and Eunice, 1940-1942 (Box 8, Folder 137)
    - Dwight Hall Peace Committee, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 138)
    - E (Box 8, Folder 139)
    - East and West Hebron United Presbyterian Church, Salem, NY, 1968-1978 (Box 8, Folder 140)
    - Encyclopedia of Sikhism, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 141)
    - Evangelisti, Archbishop Joseph B., 1970 (Box 8, Folder 142)
    - Evans, James L., 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 143)
    - Ewing Christian College, 1945-1948 (Box 8, Folder 144)
    - Ewing Christian College, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 145)
    - Ewing Christian College, 1951-1969 (Box 8, Folder 146)
    - F (Box 8, Folder 147)
    - Fellowship of Reconciliation, 1937-1939 (Box 8, Folder 148)
    - Fellowship of Reconciliation, 1940-1944 (Box 8, Folder 149)
    - Ferger, Rev. and Mrs. Henri R., 1947-1975 (Box 9, Folder 150)
    - Finch, Henry Leroy, 1941, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 151,152)
    - First Church of Christ, New Haven, CT, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 153)
    - First Presbyterian Church, Albany, NY, 1975-1978 (Box 9, Folder 154)
    - First Presbyterian Church, Ilion, NY, 1961-1976 (Box 9, Folder 155-156)
    - First Presbyterian Church, Lowville, NY, 1961-1974 (Box 9, Folder 157)
    - First Presbyterian Church, Quincy, MA, 1955-1972 (Box 9, Folder 158-160)
    - First Presbyterian Church of Brunswick, Troy, NY, 1969-1981 (Box 9, Folder 161)
    - First United Presbyterian Church, Los Gatos, CA, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 162)
    - Fordham, Tyrell D., 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 163)
    - Forman, Charles W., 1948-1983 (Box 9, Folder 164)
    - Fulbright, J. William, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 165)
    - "Friends" [circular letters from JPA], 1945-1978 (Box 9, Folder 166)
    - G (Box 9, Folder 167)
    - Gandhi, Indira [also includes letter to Prime Minister of India], 1950, 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 168)
    - Giamatti, A. Bartlett, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 169)
    - Gould, Sigrid, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 170)
    - Greenway, Mr., 1942 (Box 9, Folder 171)
    - Grier, Rev. Louis N. Jr., 1980-1982 (Box 9, Folder 172)
    - H (Box 9, Folder 173)
    - Hallett, Alfred W., 1973 (Box 9, Folder 174)
    - Hamilton, Alan H., 1963 (Box 9, Folder 175)
    - Harper, Ed and Rikki, 1955-1981 (Box 9, Folder 176)
    - Haydenburg, Tennessee [miscellaneous correspondence while serving under auspices of Presbyterian Church Board of National Missions], 1943 (Box 10, Folder 177)
    - Hayes, Mabell S., 1955-1974 (Box 10, Folder 178)
    - Hazen Foundation, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 179)
    - Hazlett, Cal H., 1948-1963 (Box 10, Folder 180)
    - Hein, Norvin, 1964-1965, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 181)
    - Henry Luce Foundation, Inc., 1982 (Box 10, Folder 182)
    - Hogg, W. Richey, 1954-1974 (Box 10, Folder 183)
    - I (Box 10, Folder 184)
    - India - Pakistan War, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 185)
    - India Council of the United Church of North India, 1953-1963 (Box 10, Folder 186)
    - India Council, cont., 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 187)
    - Indian Church History Review, 1970-1977 (Box 10, Folder 188)
    - Indian Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, 1959-1973 (Box 10, Folder 189)
    - Institute for Ecumenical and Cultural Research, 1971-1983 (Box 10, Folder 190)
    - J (Box 10, Folder 191)
    - Johnson, Helen and Jack, 1974-1979 (Box 10, Folder 192)
    - Jones, William W., 1976-1978 (Box 10, Folder 193)
    - Joseph, Wise B., 1963-1969 (Box 10, Folder 194)
    - Journal of Presbyterian History, 1971-1975 (Box 10, Folder 195)
    - K (Box 10, Folder 196)
    - Kahn, Mabel, 1963-1970 (Box 10, Folder 197)
    - Kellogg, Ralph N., 1974 (Box 10, Folder 198)
    - Kennedy, Edward M., Senator, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 199)
    - Keyser, Marjorye, 1978-1982 (Box 10, Folder 200)
    - Kitchen, William J., 1941-1942 (Box 10, Folder 201)
    - Koehler, Rev. Norman E., 1967 (Box 10, Folder 202)
    - Kutar, Dr. and Mrs. Zal, 1978-1982 (Box 10, Folder 203)
    - L (Box 10, Folder 204)
    - Lal, Right Rev. Anand C., 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 205)
    - Diocese of Amritsar (Box 10)
    - Lamar, Rev. Robert C., 1968-1974 (Box 10, Folder 206)
    - Latourette, Kenneth S., 1943-1964 (Box 10)
    - Leavy, Stanley and Margaret, 1942-1978 (Box 11, Folder 207)
    - Leiper, Hal, 1940-1947 (Box 11, Folder 208)
    - Lilly Endowment, Inc., 1982 (Box 11, Folder 209)
    - Loes, Kurt and Chand (Stephens), 1981-1982 (Box 11, Folder 210)
    - Love, Dr. Paul, 1978-1979 (Box 11, Folder 211)
    - Lovett, Sidney, 1939-1941, 1964 (Box 11)
    - Lucknow Publishing House, Lucknow, India, 1963-1976 (Box 11, Folder 212)
    - M (Box 11, Folder 213)
    - MacCune Scholarship Fund, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 214)
    - MacLeod, Beatrice, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 215)
    - Madden, Fran, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 216)
    - Masih, Prakash, 1969-1982 (Box 11, Folder 217)
    - Massey, Rev. D. B., 1970-1971 (Box 11, Folder 218)
    - Mathai, M. M., 1968-1971 (Box 11, Folder 219)
    - McLeod, Hew and Margaret, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 220)
    - McGeary, Hazel J., 1980-1982 (Box 11, Folder 221)
    - McKenzie, Patricia, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 222)
    - McNeur, Ronald W., 1978 (Box 11, Folder 223)
    - Miller, Rev. William H., 1980 (Box 11, Folder 224)
    - Misra, Mohini, 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 225)
    - Missionary Orientation Center, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 226)
    - Mount Hermon School, MA, 1934-1978 (Box 11, Folder 227)
    - N (Box 11, Folder 228)
    - Naegel, Eric, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 229)
    - Nasir, Most Rev. E. S., 1978-1980 (Box 11, Folder 230)
    - National Council of Student Christian Associations, 1940-1945 (Box 11, Folder 231)
    - National Council of YMCA, India, Burma and Ceylon, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 232)
    - Newark Christian Ashram - summer program, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 233)
    - New York Times, Editor, 1951, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 234)
    - Nineveh Presbyterian Church, Nineveh, NY, 1975-1978 (Box 11, Folder 235)
    - O (Box 11, Folder 236)
    - Oakville Estate, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 237)
    - P (Box 11, Folder 238)
    - Parker, Allen and Dorothy, 1946-1979 (Box 11, Folder 239)
    - Peace Groups - includes: Student Peace Service, Youth Committee Against War, Keep America Out of War, 1938-1939 (Box 11, Folder 240)
    - Personal Interest Program, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 241)
    - Peterson, Dr. Robert F., 1962 (Box 12, Folder 242)
    - Phelps Community Project, 1981-1982 (Box 12, Folder 243)
    - Pickett, Bishop J. Waskom, 1965-1969 (Box 12, Folder 244)
    - Poore, John G., 1940 (Box 12, Folder 245)
    - Presbyterian Church, Ballston Spa, NY, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 246)
    - Presbyterian Church in U.S.A. - Board of Christian Education, 1939-1943 (Box 12, Folder 247)
    - Presbyterian Church in U.S.A. - Board of Foreign Missions, 1940-1944 (Box 12, Folder 248)
    - Presbyterian Church in U.S.A. - Board of Foreign Missions, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 249,250)
    - Presbyterian Church in U.S.A. - Board of Foreign Missions, 1946-1950 (Box 12, Folder 251)
    - Presbyterian Church in U.S.A. -Board of National Missions, 1942 - 1944 Aug. (Box 12, Folder 252)
    - Presbyterian Historical Society, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 253)
    - Presbyterian Life, 1953-1954, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 254)
    - Punjab National Bank, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 255)
    - R (Box 12, Folder 256)
    - Reckford, E. C. (Pete), 1971-1977 (Box 12, Folder 257)
    - Riverside Church, New York City - Fosdick Ecumenical Convocation, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 258)
    - Roberts, Dr. Richard, 1941-1942, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 259)
    - Robinson, Marjorie, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 260)
    - Rogers, Rev. C. M., 1954-1970 (Box 12, Folder 261)
    - Rolston, Right Rev. M. A. Zarine, Diocese of Chandigarh, 1966-1982 (Box 12, Folder 262)
    - Ronsheim, Milton M., 1978 (Box 12, Folder 263)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1943 (Box 12, Folder 264)
    - Roxburgh, Rymall and Betty, 1970-1981 (Box 12, Folder 265)
    - Ruff, Rev. Gordon M., 1963-1978 (Box 12, Folder 266)
    - Russell, Louisa "Weedy", 1941-1942 (Box 12, Folder 267)
    - S (Box 13, Folder 268)
    - Selective Service, 1941-1943 (Box 13, Folder 269)
    - Seymour, Charles, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 270)
    - Shaffer, Helen, 1974-1975 (Box 13, Folder 271)
    - Sham, Rao P. D., 1978-1979 (Box 13, Folder 272)
    - Sharpless, Mary Lou, 1940-1947 (Box 13, Folder 273)
    - Singh, Rev. Dharam Vir, 1968-1982 (Box 13, Folder 274)
    - Singh, Ram, 1948-1980 (Box 13, Folder 275)
    - Smith, Rev. Caldwell, 1955-1972 (Box 13, Folder 276)
    - Socialist Groups - includes: Socialist Party, U.S.A., Young Peoples Socialist League, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 277)
    - Sojwal, B. J., 1974 (Box 13, Folder 278)
    - Speaking Appointments - miscellaneous correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 13, Folder 279)
    - Stephens, Nelson E., 1980-1981 (Box 13, Folder 280)
    - Stewart, George, 1941-1942 (Box 13, Folder 281)
    - Strickler, Mildred and Thomas, 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 282)
    - Student Christian Movement of New England, 1938-1940 (Box 13, Folder 283)
    - Student Christian Movement of New England, 1941-1943 (Box 13, Folder 284)
    - Student Christian Movement of New England: corres. to friend, "Johny", 1940-1942 (Box 13, Folder 285)
    - Student Volunteer Movement, 1940-1949 (Box 13, Folder 286)
    - Swarthmore Presbyterian Church, Swarthmore PA, 1948-1982 (Box 13, Folder 287-292)
    - Swift, Charles R. and Mary Lou, 1941-1979 (Box 14, Folder 293-294)
    - Swope, Joan, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 295)
    - T (Box 14, Folder 296)
    - Taylor, Mae Ross, 1958-1963 (Box 14, Folder 297)
    - Taylor, Richard W., 1969-1975 (Box 14, Folder 298)
    - Third Presbyterian Church, Elizabeth NJ, 1954-1980 (Box 14, Folder 299-302)
    - Thomas, M. M., 1968-1980 (Box 14, Folder 303)
    - Thomas, Winburn, 1943-1944 (Box 14, Folder 304)
    - Thurber, L. Newton, 1980-1983 (Box 14, Folder 305)
    - Tucker, Luther, 1941-1982 (Box 14, Folder 306)
    - U (Box 14, Folder 307)
    - Union Presbyterian Church, Endicott, NY, 1968-1983 (Box 14, Folder 308-309)
    - United Church of North India, 1955 (Box 14, Folder 310)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Black, Ada, 1968-1976 (Box 14, Folder 311)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Correspondence to Alters in India, including correspondence related to their India property, 1968-1978 (Box 14, Folder 312,313)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: McCloud, Dr. J. Oscar, 1974-1978 (Box 15, Folder 314)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Miller, Rev. William H., 1974 (Box 15, Folder 315)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Personal Interest Program, 1971-1978 (Box 15, Folder 316)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Presbytery of Albany, 1968-1974 (Box 15, Folder 317)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Presbytery of Connecticut Valley, 1969-1977 (Box 15, Folder 318)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Presbytery of Cumberland Mountain, 1949-1964 (Box 15, Folder 319)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Presbytery of Saint Andrew, 1964-1968 (Box 15, Folder 320)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Presbytery of Southern New England, 1978-1983 (Box 15, Folder 321)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Presbytery of Upper Ohio Valley, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 322)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Wilson, Rev. Frederick R., 1973-1980 (Box 15, Folder 323)
    - United Presbyterian Church in U.S.A.: Wilson, Stanton R., 1980 (Box 15, Folder 324)
    - United Presbyterian Peace Fellowship, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 325)
    - United Provinces Christian Council, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 326)